<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks on Terence Dores Cruz - Postdoctoral Researcher</title>
    <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks on Terence Dores Cruz - Postdoctoral Researcher</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 02:40:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Symposium The Functions of Gossip - Novel Insights from the Lab and the Field</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/easp-gossip-symp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 02:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/easp-gossip-symp/</guid>
      <description>I organized a symposium on the functions of gossip based on recent insights across experiments in the lab and studies in the field. The symposium includes 5 talks taking using diverse methods to study functions gossip. In the symposium, I present my work on how people use gossip strategically to shape how receivers of gossip behave towards gossip targets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welk nut heeft roddelen?</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/scicafeenschede/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/scicafeenschede/</guid>
      <description>Discussion of the definition of gossip, presentation of results from experience sampling and experimental studies for a broad audience.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Het Nut van Roddelen</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/socialanimal/socialanimal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/socialanimal/socialanimal/</guid>
      <description>Popular Science Talk on Gossip in Everyday Life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wat is roddelen en waarom doen we dat?</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/filcafedelft/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/filcafedelft/</guid>
      <description>Discussion of the definition of gossip, presentation of results from experience sampling and experimental studies for a broad audience.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding and Studying Gossip</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/uvasocialminds/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/uvasocialminds/</guid>
      <description>Presentation of results from the gossip in everyday life paper and discussion of experience sampling methods (to study gossip)/</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defining and Studying (Organizational) Gossip</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/cbop_uq_talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/cbop_uq_talk/</guid>
      <description>The omnipresence of workplace gossip makes understanding gossip processes imperative to understand social life in organizations. Although gossip research has recently increased across the social sciences, gossip is conceptualized in disparate ways in the scientific literature. This conceptual confusion impedes theoretical integration and providing practical advice. To resolve this, we systematically reviewed 6114 scientific articles on gossip and identified 324 articles that define gossip. From these definitions, we extracted two essential characteristics of gossip on which there seems to be agreement within the literature, namely, (1) that gossip is communication between humans involving a sender, a receiver, and a target, and (2) that the target is absent or unaware of the communicated content. These two characteristics formed the basis of a broad, integrative definition of gossip: a sender communicating to a receiver about a target who is absent or unaware of the content. Furthermore, some definitions include characteristics on which there is less agreement: gossip valence (from negative to neutral to positive) and formality (from informal to intermediate to formal). We incorporate these characteristics in a dimensional scaling framework that can guide future research. Our broad, integrative definition of gossip and the dimensional scaling framework provide the building blocks for a systematic, integrated knowledge base on the role of gossip in human social life in general as well as in organizations. This can foster future theory development and hypothesis testing, ultimately helping organizations to manage gossip.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Costs and Benefits of Gossip</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/crisp_uq_talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/crisp_uq_talk/</guid>
      <description>While existing work has shown that people do readily share gossip in anonymous lab settings, there is also evidence that gossipers may face social disapproval (Adams &amp;amp; Mullen, 2012), especially if the information that they share describes a target negatively. This presents a conundrum: if there are social costs to sharing gossip, then individuals will be better off if staying silent and free-riding on the gossip shared by others. Yet, if everyone stays silent, the reputation system will no longer be useful and will break down, inhibiting reputation-based cooperation. This suggests that gossip may be a second-order social dilemma. That is, gossip could be a solution to first-order social dilemmas by introducing reputational benefits and costs to cooperation and defection. Yet, if sharing gossip is socially costly for gossipers while conferring collective benefits, people may refrain from gossip.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gossip and Reputation in Everyday Life</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/cep_uq_talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/cep_uq_talk/</guid>
      <description>Gossip—a sender communicating to a receiver about an absent third party—is hypothesized to impact reputation formation, partner selection, and cooperation. Laboratory experiments have found that people gossip about others&amp;rsquo; cooperativeness and that they use gossip to condition their cooperation. Here, we move beyond the laboratory and test several predictions from theories of indirect reciprocity and reputation-based partner selection about the content of everyday gossip and how people use it to update the reputation of others in their social network. In a Dutch community sample (N = 309), we sampled daily events in which people either sent or received gossip about a target over 10 days (ngossip = 5284). Gossip senders frequently shared information about targets’ cooperativeness and did so in ways that minimize potential retaliation from targets. Receivers overwhelmingly believed gossip to be true and updated their evaluation of targets based on gossip. In turn, a positive shift in the evaluation of a target was associated with higher intentions to help them in future interactions, and with lower intentions to avoid them in the future. Thus, gossip is used in daily life to impact and update reputations in a way that enables partner selection and indirect reciprocity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Punishing or Praising Gossipers - How People Interpret the Motives Driving Gossip Shapes its Consequences</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/icsd-reactions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/icsd-reactions/</guid>
      <description>Since gossip has been shown to benefit group cooperation, gossipers should be rewarded for gossiping. In contrast, gossiping is commonly perceived negatively, implying that gossipers incur costs rather than benefits. To solve this puzzle, we argue that how receivers attribute gossip to pro-social versus pro-self motives shapes their reactions towards gossipers. To test this, we conducted a pre-registered experimental vignette study (n = 1188) in which participants received negative gossip statements, which we manipulated to reflect either pro-self or pro-social motives. Supporting our predictions, results showed that when receivers attributed negative gossip to pro-social (vs pro-self) motives, they trusted gossipers more, and targets less (for behavioral as well as attitudinal measures of trust). Furthermore, receivers were more likely to mistakenly attribute pro-social gossip to pro-self motives than vice versa, but those with a higher ability to overcome intuition were better able to correctly distinguish pro-self and pro-social motives for gossip.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nasty and Noble Notes - Interdependence Structure drives Self-Serving Gossip</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/aspo-spd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/aspo-spd/</guid>
      <description>Talk on the results of a interactive lab experiment showing how the interdependence structure in which gossip occurs drives prosocial and proself motives for gossip.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roddelen en Reputatie in het Dagelijks Leven</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/sepxtalknip/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/sepxtalknip/</guid>
      <description>Talk for a broader audience (in Dutch) about my work on gossip and reputation in everyday life</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gossip and Reputation in Everyday Life</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/klibestpaper/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2022 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/klibestpaper/</guid>
      <description>Gossip—a sender communicating to a receiver about an absent third party—is hypothesized to impact reputation formation, partner selection, and cooperation. Laboratory experiments have found that people gossip about others&amp;rsquo; cooperativeness and that they use gossip to condition their cooperation. Here, we move beyond the laboratory and test several predictions from theories of indirect reciprocity and reputation-based partner selection about the content of everyday gossip and how people use it to update the reputation of others in their social network. In a Dutch community sample (N = 309), we sampled daily events in which people either sent or received gossip about a target over 10 days (ngossip = 5284). Gossip senders frequently shared information about targets’ cooperativeness and did so in ways that minimize potential retaliation from targets. Receivers overwhelmingly believed gossip to be true and updated their evaluation of targets based on gossip. In turn, a positive shift in the evaluation of a target was associated with higher intentions to help them in future interactions, and with lower intentions to avoid them in the future. Thus, gossip is used in daily life to impact and update reputations in a way that enables partner selection and indirect reciprocity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nasty and Noble Notes - How Interdependence Structure drives Prosocial and Proself Gossip [CANCELED]</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/prosproslabaspocancel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Dec 2021 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/prosproslabaspocancel/</guid>
      <description>Talk on the results of a interactive lab experiment showing how the interdependence structure in which gossip occurs drives prosocial and proself motives for gossip.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nasty and Noble Notes - How Interdependence Structure drives Prosocial and Proself Gossip</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/prosocial-proself-motives-lab/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2021 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/prosocial-proself-motives-lab/</guid>
      <description>Talk on the results of a interactive lab experiment showing how the interdependence structure in which gossip occurs drives prosocial and proself motives for gossip.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Symposium The Psychology of Gossip - Cooperative and Competitive Functions</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/hbes-gossip-symp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 02:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/hbes-gossip-symp/</guid>
      <description>I organized a symposium on how gossip can have both cooperative (or prosocial) or competitve (or proself) functions. The symposium includes 4 talks taking an evolutionary perspective on the functions gossip. In the symposium, I present my work on how gossip and reputation in everyday life can function to enable reputation-based cooperation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gossip about Coronavirus - Infection status and norm adherence shape social responses [CANCELED]</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/covid-gos-hbes-cancel/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/covid-gos-hbes-cancel/</guid>
      <description>Poster showing resutls of an online vignette study how gossip about adherence to norms regarding Coronavirus and symptoms of Coronavirus shape how receivers of gossip perceive targets.as well as how they would behave towards targets</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>People Gossip Strategically to Shape Receiver Behavior [CANCELED]</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/stratgos-hbes-cancel/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/stratgos-hbes-cancel/</guid>
      <description>Talk showing everyday gossip fits with indirect reciprocity and partner choice theories, indicating senders can use gossip to strategically shape receiver&amp;rsquo;s behavior.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Psychology of Gossip</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/ocean-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/ocean-talk/</guid>
      <description>Overview of my recent research on gossip through the lens of evolutionary, social, and organizational psychology</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gossip and Reputation in Everyday Life</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/ehbea-gossip-in-daily-life-poster/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/ehbea-gossip-in-daily-life-poster/</guid>
      <description>Poster on the results of a large experience sampling study showing people in daily life gossip in ways that support indirect reciprocity and partner selection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nasty and Noble Notes - Interdependence drives prosocial and proself gossip</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/spd-poster-spsp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2021 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/spd-poster-spsp/</guid>
      <description>Poster on the results of a large interactive lab experiment showing people gossip for both prosocial and proself motives. We demonstrate that the interdependence structure within the gossip triad influences which motives are displayed</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gossip and Reputation in Everyday Life</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/datablitzspspevo-pre-experience-sampling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 15:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/datablitzspspevo-pre-experience-sampling/</guid>
      <description>Data blitz on the results of a large experience sampling study showing people in daily life gossip in ways that support indirect reciprocity and partner selection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gossip in Groups (with Annika Nieper)</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/colloquium-hamburg/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2020 15:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/colloquium-hamburg/</guid>
      <description>We will present an overview of our projects with the ERC Force of Gossip Group</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gossip and Reputation in Everyday Life [CANCELED]</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/expsamp-aspo-video/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2020 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/expsamp-aspo-video/</guid>
      <description>Blitz talk about the results of a large experience sampling study of gossip in daily life promoting reputation-based cooperation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gossip and Reputation in Everyday Life</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/datablitzcben-experience-sampling/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Nov 2020 15:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/datablitzcben-experience-sampling/</guid>
      <description>Data blitz on the results of a large experience sampling study showing people in daily life gossip in ways that support indirect reciprocity and partner selection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Symposium on The Functions of Gossip - Insights from the Lab and the Field [CANCELLED]</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/easp-gossip-symp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/easp-gossip-symp/</guid>
      <description>I organized a symposium in which we provide novel empirical insights from the lab and the field into the functions of gossip. We would present 4 talks and discussant, among which my work on how senders of gossip strategically share information to impact how receivers of gossip behave towards targets of gossip.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Perceiving, Communicating, and Enforcing Norms about COVID-19</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/isr-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/isr-talk/</guid>
      <description>Short talk for a broader audience (in Dutch) about work on norms around COVID-19</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strategic Behavior through a Group’s Grapevine - Gossip between Group Members Shapes Receiver Behavior</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/spsp-strategicgossip/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2020 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/spsp-strategicgossip/</guid>
      <description>Poster showing everyday gossip fits with indirect reciprocity and partner choice theories, indicating senders can use gossip to strategically shape group member behavior.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gossip and Reputation in Everyday Life</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/aspo-gossip-in-daily-life-poster-aspo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2019 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/aspo-gossip-in-daily-life-poster-aspo/</guid>
      <description>Poster on the results of a large experience sampling study showing people in daily life gossip in ways that support indirect reciprocity and partner selection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Selfish and Prosocial Motives for Gossip</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/prosocial-proself-motives-mturk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2019 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/prosocial-proself-motives-mturk/</guid>
      <description>The results of a online scenario study showing that different outcomes for gossipers can lead to proself versus prosocial motives to gossip.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gossip and Reputation in Everyday Life</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/gossip-in-daily-life-poster-cben/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2019 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/gossip-in-daily-life-poster-cben/</guid>
      <description>Poster on the results of a large experience sampling study showing people in daily life gossip in ways that support indirect reciprocity and partner selection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Embezzlement Game</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/embezzlementgame/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2019 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/embezzlementgame/</guid>
      <description>The Adverse Interaction between Psychopathy and Transparency on Corrupt Behavior</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gossip and Reputation in Everyday Life</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/gossip-in-daily-life-poster/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2019 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/gossip-in-daily-life-poster/</guid>
      <description>Poster on the results of a large experience sampling study showing people in daily life gossip in ways that support indirect reciprocity and partner selection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gossip in Daily Life</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/gossip-in-daily-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2019 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/gossip-in-daily-life/</guid>
      <description>The results of a large experience sampling study showing people in daily life gossip in ways that support indirect reciprocity and partner selection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gossip in Daily Life</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/gossip-in-daily-life-workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2018 08:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/gossip-in-daily-life-workshop/</guid>
      <description>The results of a large experience sampling study showing people in daily life gossip in ways that support indirect reciprocity and partner selection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Punishing or Praising Gossipers - How People Interpret the Motives Driving Gossip Shapes its Consequences</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/phd-poster-session/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/phd-poster-session/</guid>
      <description>Since gossip has been shown to benefit group cooperation, gossipers should be rewarded for gossiping. In contrast, gossiping is commonly perceived negatively, implying that gossipers incur costs rather than benefits. To solve this puzzle, we argue that how receivers attribute gossip to pro-social versus pro-self motives shapes their reactions towards gossipers. To test this, we conducted a pre-registered experimental vignette study (n = 1188) in which participants received negative gossip statements, which we manipulated to reflect either pro-self or pro-social motives. Supporting our predictions, results showed that when receivers attributed negative gossip to pro-social (vs pro-self) motives, they trusted gossipers more, and targets less (for behavioral as well as attitudinal measures of trust). Furthermore, receivers were more likely to mistakenly attribute pro-social gossip to pro-self motives than vice versa, but those with a higher ability to overcome intuition were better able to correctly distinguish pro-self and pro-social motives for gossip.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Punishing or Praising Gossipers - How People Interpret the Motives Driving Gossip Shapes its Consequences</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/reactionsacl/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/talk/reactionsacl/</guid>
      <description>Since gossip has been shown to benefit group cooperation, gossipers should be rewarded for gossiping. In contrast, gossiping is commonly perceived negatively, implying that gossipers incur costs rather than benefits. To solve this puzzle, we argue that how receivers attribute gossip to pro-social versus pro-self motives shapes their reactions towards gossipers. To test this, we conducted a pre-registered experimental vignette study (n = 1188) in which participants received negative gossip statements, which we manipulated to reflect either pro-self or pro-social motives. Supporting our predictions, results showed that when receivers attributed negative gossip to pro-social (vs pro-self) motives, they trusted gossipers more, and targets less (for behavioral as well as attitudinal measures of trust). Furthermore, receivers were more likely to mistakenly attribute pro-social gossip to pro-self motives than vice versa, but those with a higher ability to overcome intuition were better able to correctly distinguish pro-self and pro-social motives for gossip.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>