<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bianca Beersma on Terence Dores Cruz - PhD Candidate</title>
    <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/authors/bianca-beersma/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bianca Beersma on Terence Dores Cruz - PhD Candidate</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 31 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://terencedorescruz.com/authors/bianca-beersma/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>An Integrative Definition and Framework to Study Gossip</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/gossipdefined_preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/gossipdefined_preprint/</guid>
      <description>We systematically reviewed of all definition of gossip in the scientific literature. First, we define gossip as a sender communicating to a receiver about a target, who is absent or unaware of  the content. Second, we propose an integrative to study gossip as varying in valence and formality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gossip and Reputation in Everyday Life</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/gossipreputationineverydaylife-preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/gossipreputationineverydaylife-preprint/</guid>
      <description>Large experience sampling study showing people use gossip in daily life gossip efficiently impact and update reputations in a way that enables partner selection and indirect reciprocity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting a Grip on the Grapevine: Extension and Factor Structure of the Motives to Gossip Questionnaire</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/mtg-cfa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/mtg-cfa/</guid>
      <description>The Motives to Gossip Questionnaire was extended with an emotion venting scale. The five factor structure was supported and fully invariant across gossip definitions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bright and Dark Side of Gossip for Cooperation in Groups</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/brightdarksidegossip/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/brightdarksidegossip/</guid>
      <description>Two studies indicate gossip has positive and negative aspects for cooperation in groups, these aspects depend on situational factors and agent perspectives.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>