<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications on Terence Dores Cruz - PhD Candidate</title>
    <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publications on Terence Dores Cruz - PhD Candidate</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How political orientation, economic precarity, and participant demographics impact compliance with COVID-19 prevention measures in a Dutch representative sample</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/kieskompas-covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/kieskompas-covid/</guid>
      <description>Our results suggest that political, demographic, and economic precarity related predictors are important in shaping measure compliance as well as attitudes and policy support and should all be considered for a comprehensive understanding of individuals’ responses to COVID-19 measures.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hostile media perceptionaffects news bias, but not news sharing intentions</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/hostilemediaperception/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/hostilemediaperception/</guid>
      <description>Partisans perceive neutral coverage of news by outlets opposite to their political leaning as biased, even when we account for their prior beliefs regarding the media outlet and news content.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prosocial and punishment behaviors in everyday life</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/prosocialpunishmenteverydaylife/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/prosocialpunishmenteverydaylife/</guid>
      <description>Review paper outlining how research can benefit from studying prosocial and punishment behaviors in daily life using experience sampling and diary methods that document natural phenomena.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gossip and Reputation in Everyday Life</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/gossipreputationineverydaylife-preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/gossipreputationineverydaylife-preprint/</guid>
      <description>Large experience sampling study showing people use gossip in daily life gossip efficiently impact and update reputations in a way that enables partner selection and indirect reciprocity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Honesty and dishonesty in gossip strategies: a fitness interdependence analysis</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/honestdishoneststrategiesgossip/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/honestdishoneststrategiesgossip/</guid>
      <description>Theoretical paper outlining when gossiper should share honest versus dishonest information based on the interdependence structure in which gossip occurs and the marginal costs/benefits of gossip</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Integrative Definition and Framework to Study Gossip</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/gossipdefined_preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/gossipdefined_preprint/</guid>
      <description>We systematically reviewed of all definition of gossip in the scientific literature. First, we define gossip as a sender communicating to a receiver about a target, who is absent or unaware of  the content. Second, we propose an integrative to study gossip as varying in valence and formality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gossip about Coronavirus: Infection status and norm adherence shape social responses </title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/covid_gossip/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/covid_gossip/</guid>
      <description>We presented participants with gossip relevant to the Coronavirus pandemic. Results showed people tended to believe gossip and that gossip influenced behavioral intentions to avoid and punish targets of gossip as well as the perception of targets. We conclude that gossip, while potentially unreliable, could affect how people treat group members.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A creative destruction approach to replication: Implicit work and sex morality across cultures</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/consortiumcreativedescrution/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/consortiumcreativedescrution/</guid>
      <description>Work is intuitively moralized across cultures.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disgust Anger, and Aggression: Further Tests of the Equivalence of Moral Emotions</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/angerdisgustagressionpreprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/angerdisgustagressionpreprint/</guid>
      <description>Disgust (but not anger) was related to indirect aggression whereas anger (but not disgust) was related to direct aggression, and disgust was higher toward other-targeting violations whereas anger was higher toward self-targeting violations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting a Grip on the Grapevine: Extension and Factor Structure of the Motives to Gossip Questionnaire</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/mtg-cfa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/mtg-cfa/</guid>
      <description>The Motives to Gossip Questionnaire was extended with an emotion venting scale. The five factor structure was supported and fully invariant across gossip definitions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bright and Dark Side of Gossip for Cooperation in Groups</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/brightdarksidegossip/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/brightdarksidegossip/</guid>
      <description>Two studies indicate gossip has positive and negative aspects for cooperation in groups, these aspects depend on situational factors and agent perspectives.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Look Over Your Shoulder: Unethical Behaviour Decreases in the Physical Presence of Observers</title>
      <link>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/lookovershoulder-preprint/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://terencedorescruz.com/publication/lookovershoulder-preprint/</guid>
      <description>The presence of an observing others curbs unethical behavior, while mere presence of an (unobserving other does not. The influence of an observing other is not qualified by payoff structure or social proximity.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>